Register of the Ernest Lloyd Harris papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ernest Lloyd Harris papers
1894-1930
XX072
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (2.6 linear feet)
Reports, memoranda, and correspondence relating to the Russian Civil War in Siberia, the Czechoslovak Legion, political and economic conditions in Siberia, and American policy in Siberia.
Harris, Ernest Lloyd, 1870-1946.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1870 October 26 Born, Jasper County, Iowa
1891 Ph.B., Cornell College, Iowa
1895 A.M., Ph.D., University of Heidelberg
1896 J.U.D., University of Heidelberg
1896 Lecturer on Jurisprudence, State University of Iowa
1898 Consular Agent, Eibenstock, Germany
1902 Commercial Agent, Eibenstock, Germany
1905-1906 Consul at Chemnitz, Germany
1905-1906 Lecturer on commerce, University of Chicago
1906-1908 Consul at Smyrna Turkey
1908-1911 Consul General, Smyrna, Turkey
1911-1916 Consul General, Stockholm
1917 Staff, National City Bank of New York, Moscow branch
1918-1921 Consul General, Irkutsk, Siberia
1921-1925 Consul General, Singapore
1925-1929 Consul General, Vancouver, British Columbia
1929-1935 Consul General, Vienna
1935 Retired from the Foreign Service
1946 February 2 Died, Vancouver, British Columbia
Scope and Content of Collection
Reports, memoranda, and correspondence relating to the Russian Civil War in Siberia, the Czechoslovak Legion, political and economic conditions in Siberia, and American policy in Siberia.
Russia. Armiia. Československý střelecký pluk..; United States. Consulate General (Irkutsk, Russia); Czechoslovakia.; Diplomats--United States.; Russia (Federation); Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1909-1930 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters sent and received by Ernest Lloyd Harris, arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
  - Finocchi, Guido, 1919 August 20 (Box 1)
  - Fowler, W. B., 1920 March 31
  - Grovesnor, Gilbert H., 1909 January 15
  - Lutz, Professor Ralph J., 1930 March 17
  - Morris, Ambassador Roland S., 1919 May 7
  - Pollak, R., 1920 April 26
  - Semenov, Ataman G., 1920 February 28
  - Thomas, Edward B., 1920 Mary 24
  - U.S. Secretary of State, 1918 September 9
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1924 (Boxes 1-2)
  Reports, protocols, and clippings, arranged alphabetically by subject or title.
  - Border, Russian-Chinese, inspection (Box 1)
  - Chita, conditions in
  - Consulates, U.S.
    - Finances
    - Personnel
    - Reports of consuls
  - Cooperatives, Russian and Siberian
  - Cotton in Russia
    - Preliminary report
    - Supplemental report
  - Czecho-Slovak Legion
    - Actions in Siberia, 1918, consular reports
    - Bolsheviks, relations with
    - Conversations and conferences
    - "The Czecho-Slavok [sic] Incident," official version by the Temporary Executive Committee of the Czecho-Slovak Army, 1918
    - "The Czecho-Slovak Revolutionary Movement," speech by Kenneth D. Miller, Young Men's Christian Association, undated
    - Fourth-of-July greetings to U.S. President
    - "History of the Czechoslovak Legion in Russia," book review (author unknown)
    - Kolchak army, relation to
    - "Manifesto to the Inhabitants of Siberia," by the Information Department of the Czech Forces in Siberia (translation), 1920
    - Political role
    - Press reports
    - Trains
    - "The Truth about the Czechoslovak Legions in Siberia," article by Jaroslav Papousek in the Central European Observer, Prague, 1933 April 14
    - U.S. attitude
    - "With the Czecho-Slovacks [sic] from Mariensk to Neusneuodinsk [sic]," report by Ernest F. Campbell, 1918 June-July
    - "Zborov--the Revolutionary Movement of Czehs-Slovaks [sic]" (author unknown), circa 1918 June
  - Economy, Russian and Siberian (Box 2)
    - Agriculture
    - Currency
    - Effects of Revolution
    - Trade
  - Entente, policy towards Russia
  - German-Japanese Treaty, draft
  - Intervention, Allied
  - Irkutsk
    - Conditions
    - Socialist-Revolutionary/Zemstvo Party uprising
  - Janin, General Pierre
  - Joint Distribution Committee, relief work in Siberia
  - Kolchak, Admiral Alexamder Vasilevich
    - Allies' relation to
    - Arrest and execution
    - Government
  - Korean National Council
  - Krasnoyarsk, events in
  - McCroskey, Lt. Col. B. B., mission of
  - Nizhneudinsk, Menshevik government at
  - Omsk
    - Evacuation
    - Political situation, 1918 May-November
    - Socialist-Revolutionaries killed at
  - Passports
  - Perm, conditions in (report of French Military Mission in Siberia)
  - Petrov, Minister N. I., address of
  - Property, American, in Russia and Siberia
  - Publicity, U.S.
  - Railroads
  - Red Cross
  - Russia
    - Imperial Family
    - "The Political Situation in Russia," article by Vladimir Dillon, undated
  - Semenov, Ataman G.
  - Serbian refugees
  - Siberia, government of
  - Soviet Federal Republic, governmental plan
  - Tredwell, R.
  - U.S. - Soviet relations
  - Verkhneudinsk, situation in
  - Vladisvostok, hostilities in
  - Voitsekhovskii, Major General (first name unknown)
  - Wild Division (Mongol-Buriat division under Ataman Semenov, commanded by General Levitskii), atrocities committed by Young Men's Christian Association
- TELEGRAMS, 1918-1921 (Boxes 3-5)
  Copies of telegrams sent and received by the office of Ernest Lloyd Harris, U.S. Consul General in Siberia, arranged alphabetically by name of office or last name of person, chronologically thereunder. Outgoing telegrams are filed by date sent, incoming telegrams by date received, if indicated.
  - American Consulates, general circulars, 1918 (Box 3)
  - American Consulate, Chita, 1920
  - American Consulate, Ekaterinburg, 1918
  - American Consulate, Harbin, 1920
  - American Consulate, Irkutsk, 1918-1919
  - American Consulate, Omsk, 1918-1919
  - American Consulate, Samara, 1918
  - American Consulate, Tomsk, 1918-1919
  - American Consulate, Ufa, 1918
  - American Consulate, Vladisvostok
    - 1918
    - 1919 January-March
    - 1919 April-June
    - 1919 July-September
    - 1919 October-December
    - 1920
  - American Legation, Peking
    - 1918 June-September
    - 1918 October-December (Box 4)
    - 1919 January
    - 1919 February
    - 1919 March
    - 1919 April
    - 1919 May
    - 1919 June
    - 1919 July
    - 1919 August
    - 1919 September
    - 1919 October
    - 1919 November
    - 1919 December
    - 1920 January
  - American Minister, Peking (Box 5)
  - American Red Cross
  - American Vice-Consulate, Krasnoyarsk
  - Dillon, Vladimir E.
  - Emerson, Colonel George H.
  - Glaman, Vice-Consul Otto T.
  - Graves, Major General William S.
  - Morris, Ambassador Roland S.
  - Morrow, Colonel C. H.
  - Stevens, John F.
  - U.S. Department of State
    - General file
    - Secretary of State
- WRITINGS, 1894-1924 (Box 5)
  Writings of Ernest Lloyd Harris on Siberia and other topics, arranged alphabetically by title or, in absence thereof, by subject.
  - "The Allies in Siberia," carbon copy of incomplete typewritten manuscript, 1921 (Box 5)
  - "Beginnings of the Czecho-Slovak Anabasis," article by Consul General Harris, undated
  - "Church and State in the Maryland Colony," published dissertation, Heidelberg, 1894
  - "The Consular Corps in Siberia," incomplete handwritten manuscript, undated
  - "The Czechoslovak Campaign in the Trans-Baikal," incomplete handwritten manuscript by Consul General Harris, undated
  - "The Economical Situation in Sweden," handwritten manuscript, undated
  - Lapland, carbon copy of typewritten manuscript fragment, undated
  - "The March of the Seventy Thousand," incomplete handwritten manuscript of Consul General Harris, undated
  - Raffles, Sir Stamford, Section IV of a typewritten manuscript with carbon copies, undated
  - "Recollections of a Consul General," incomplete handwritten manuscript, undated
  - "Siberia in Revolt," handwritten manuscript by Consul General Harris, undated
  - Soviet Trade, typewritten manuscript, undated
  - "Turkestan in Time of War," incomplete typewritten manuscript, undated
  - Miscellaneous writings
- MISCELLANY (Box 5)
  Letters, notes, clippings, transcripts of wire conversations, fragments of articles by Ernest Lloyd Harris, register of telegrams, humor, etc.
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 16 prints, 4 negatives / 1 envelope. (Photo file)
  16 prints, including 6 photographs of Consul General Harris' first wife; 4 group photographs including Consul General Harris, one with Admiral Kolchak and one with U.S. consular officials; 1 photograph of the entrance to the Mosque of Selim at Ephesus; and 1 photograph of Consul General Harris with his second wife.